{
  "reference_number": "10810",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Any legislation or policy must be flexible and responsive to change."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Flexibility is key to success - as the environment changes (i.e. gets worse) over time or technology advances, the budgets may need\n to be much lower (or higher) than what they're originally set to."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Should also consider the broader social and environmental impacts on health; and consider the younger generations' voices and\n\nopinions."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Communicating the process to the public - being transparent about what is going on and engaging youth on the journey could\nstrengthen the validity of the plans to the people benefiting from them. Using a responsive online tool (or even a website) to keep\n\nthe national community up-to-date could be a powerful opportunity to engage wider audiences in central government. I think it is also\nimperative and crucial that central government works with local governments (particularly regional councils) on setting plans - after all,\n\nthey will most likely be the ones using the plans to guide their policies and plans on climate change, consenting and other\nenvironmental issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I think it is also important to have expertise from the health sector and from the primary industries sector, specifically agriculture or\naquaculture. Representation from civil defence and emergency management might also be relevant, in terms of understanding scope\n\nand response to climate change weather events and how this ought to be best factored into the plans."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Very glad this is FINALLY happening. I hope that the Climate Change Commission can actually be given the powers to make positive\n\nand sustainable change. Given that the Commerce Commission has decision-making powers, then I wholeheartedly think the Climate\nChange Commission should too - for far too long commerce and economy has been given preference over the environment. In order\n\nfor this Bill to have a sustainable impact, at least give them equal representation and powers. Climate change is past the point of\nbeing political fodder, it is happening regardless of who is in power. On the consultation document: for future reports, please a font\n\nother than Calibri. Something like Helvetica Neue or even Arial would be better from a style point of view. Calibri is just the standard\nWord document template font that is so lazy and understyled, a piece of my soul dies whenever Calibri is used by government\nagencies. Please sharpen up.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
